Hello everyone!
My name is Krishna and I'm thrilled to welcome you to my comprehensive Udemy course on complete Machine
Learning and NLP with end to end projects and MLOps with over 13 plus years of experience in the data
analytics industry and more than seven plus years of teaching experience, I've had the privilege of
working with renowned companies like Panasonic, sapient, Honeywell NY and many more.
Now I am excited to share my knowledge with everyone in this course.
We will deep dive into the fascinating world of machine learning.
Starting from the basics and building up to advanced concepts.
We will cover everything from understanding the mathematical intuition behind all the machine learning
algorithms to their practical implementation, along with end to end projects.
Till deployment, you will also learn various open source tools like MLflow, DVC, Bento ML and many
more.
You will master all the machine learning algorithms such as Linear Regression, Decision Tree, Random
Forest, SVM, Naive Bias.
Along with this, we will also be learning about all the techniques that is required in understanding
natural language processing and neural networks.
We will break down the mathematics that powers this algorithm, ensuring you have a solid theoretical
understanding.
But we won't stop there.
Practical intuition is the key.
We will implement this algorithms completely from basic to advanced and see them in action through various
real world applications.
One of the unique aspects of this course is our focus on end to end projects.
You will get hands on experience with CI, CD pipeline, GitHub actions and MLOps using open source
tools like MLflow, Bento, ML and DVC.
Here we are also including cloud deployments like Azure and AWS.
By the end of this course, you will be proficient in deploying machine learning models and managing
the entire life cycle.
In this course, we will also delve into natural language processing, covering essential text pre-processing
techniques such as one hot encoding, bag of words, TF-IDF word two vec, and average word two vec.
You will gain the skills to tackle text related projects and understand the working of NLP in machine
learning.
As a bonus, I have also included a complete section of Deep Learning.
You will learn the mathematical intuition behind neural networks optimizers loss function including
convolution neural network.
This bonus content will give you a well-rounded understanding of both traditional and advanced machine
learning techniques.
So whether you are a beginner or looking to advance your skills into the data analytics industry, this
course is designed to equip you with the knowledge and practical experience you need to excel in the
field of Machine Learning and NLP.
Join me in this exciting course and let's unlock the potential of data together.
Enroll now and I will see you all in the course.
Thank you.