Hello guys.
So in this video we are going to go ahead with the installation of Anaconda and VS code which will be
our IDE, right.
If you see just an example of VS code, this is how my VS code looks like.
You know, a good, amazing, uh, complete IDE to probably execute your code.
You can execute your code both in ipynb format.
You can execute your code in.py format and all.
So this is entirely my VS code IDE, right?
So first of all, before we go ahead and install about VS code, first of all we need to go ahead and
install about Anaconda.
Anaconda is one amazing open source tool.
You know, it provides a complete open source ecosystem for sourcing, building and deploying data science
and AI initiative.
Okay, so, uh, if you really want to work with multiple environments, multiple packages.
So this will be the best thing that you will probably have in order to get started with Python programming
language.
Right.
And it is necessary that everybody uses this, you know because here the management of packages, the
management of environments will happen very much easily.
Now the importance of packages and management is very important because you may want to work with different
different versions of Python.
So for that you really need to create a different environments.
Okay, so let's get started and start with installation of Anaconda.
So first of all we will go ahead and click on Free download.
So here you can see that once I click on free download I can uh if you go down okay.
So here you will be able to see what all things it basically supports.
Right now you can provide your email address.
Let's say I'm going to provide my email address over here Krishna zero six.
At the rate gmail.com I will click on submit okay.
Once I click on submit here, you will be able to see that I'm able to get the Download Now button over
here link.
Right.
So I have windows, I have Mac, I have Linux okay.
Now based on your operating system it will automatically give whether you need to install 64 bit graphical
installer or whether you need to probably go ahead with Mac Linux.
Right?
Right now I am having windows, so I will just go ahead and click on this particular link.
So once I click on this link here you can see that this entire link is basically getting downloaded.
Once it gets downloaded, we'll start the installation.
Okay, so I hope everybody remembers this specific step.
So first of all we need to go ahead and go to anaconda.com.
Click on free downloads, provide your email ID and just go ahead and go to this Download Now option.
And whichever is your operating system just go ahead and click on Download Now okay.
So once this is done, the next step that you can specifically do over here is that you can see that
my Anaconda exe file is ready.
I will double click on this and I will start my installation.
So here you can see I have already started my installation okay.
Setup will guide you through the installation of Anaconda three.
So and so version everything.
Then we will go ahead and click on next okay.
It will ask you for this license agreement.
So you just need to go ahead and click on I agree.
Now for if your system is basically used by multiple users, you can click on all users or you can just
click on just me right.
Since I'm using this particular workstation or laptop or anything.
I'll just click on just me so I will go ahead and click on next.
Now once I go ahead and click on next, it will ask me to select a destination folder.
Now by default, this destination folder is basically created in my C drive of Anaconda three, right?
If since Anaconda is already installed in my machine.
So here you are able to see this Anaconda three folder.
But let's say that you want to go ahead of the installation in some other folder by default.
Over here it will take the C drive, right.
If you want to go ahead with the other folder.
Also you can go ahead and select it.
Let's say that I want to probably go ahead with my desktop folder.
Here I will create my another folder.
Or let's say if I go to my E drive okay e drive here I have one Anaconda folder okay.
So please make sure that you write this Anaconda three because it needs to be matching with this right
in my C drive by default it is basically creating this Anaconda three folder okay.
But I want it to have it in E drive.
Let's say I'm just showing you multiple options You can also go ahead with C drive.
Also it is up to you.
So let's say I go ahead and select this.
I will write okay.
And then I will go ahead and click on next.
So here you can see that it will give you multiple option create start menu shortcuts.
Add Anaconda three to my path environment variable not recommended.
Clear the package cache upon completion.
So what I will do.
I will also make sure that I will check this box.
Okay, it is saying not recommended, but I will tell you what is the importance of this.
Because once we go to our environment variable okay.
If I just go ahead and see my environment variable, one very important thing in this particular path,
right, is to have this anaconda path.
Right.
So this paths will be automatically added in the environment variable.
And because of this particular path you know, if it is added in the environment variable, it will
be very helpful when we execute any conda command.
Right.
With the help of conda command we will be creating a new environment.
We will be doing multiple things.
And all right.
So this will be very important.
Right.
And this path is only added when you specifically when you specifically just check this particular box.
That is, add Anaconda three to my path environment variable.
This is important.
Please do make sure that you check this okay.
And then what you can actually do you can click on install.
Once you click on install this is going to take some amount of time with respect to the installation.
Once the installation will happen, wherever you have selected the folder location right there, the
installation will happen automatically.
And also make sure that whenever you see your environment variable right, that environment variable
should have this path inserted over here.
Right?
So Anaconda three.
Anaconda three library this bin folder user bin folder library bin folder and scripts.
This for path needed to be added and it will get automatically added if you have done the checkbox.
Okay.
So this is very important because of without this, trust me your command is going to fail when you
write any conda command.
Okay.
Like you want to do probably pip install.
You want to probably create an environment using conda that is not going to work.
Okay.
So once this installation is done I hope you will be able to do it.
Just please go ahead and do it.
Once the installation is done, your anaconda will be ready.
Now, once you complete the installation, I will just go ahead and click on Anaconda.
Right.
So once I write Anaconda here you will be able to see that I'll be getting this Anaconda navigator.
So I will click on Anaconda Navigator over here.
Once I click on Anaconda Navigator here is what it will get displayed.
So this will be initializing and I will be able to see one.
Amazing.
Uh, you know, this entire Anaconda navigator will be opened as a window app.
Okay.
So this is going to just take some time because once you probably do the installation, you go ahead
and just open it.
So here you can see I have opened this.
Okay.
So this is my Anaconda navigator.
So in this Anaconda navigator you have Jupiter notebook.
You can directly click on launch.
Automatically.
The Jupiter notebook will be opened.
You have other things like PyCharm.
You have data.
Uh datalore.
You have Watson Studio.
You have PyCharm professional.
All these are different different Ides.
Right.
And one of the main things is that I've already installed this anaconda.
You will be able to see that so many different different environments have created C, V and V, V and
V in different different folder location.
I will show you how to create an environment and all as we go ahead.
Okay.
Now after going ahead with this Anaconda navigator, the next thing that you need to install is your
VS code.
So in order to install the VS code I will click on VS code download.
Okay.
Then here my VS code link will be over here.
Just click on VS code download and this VS code is also available for everyone.
It is a complete open source.
So based on your operating system, whether it is windows OS or Mac, you just go ahead and install
this.
So I'll click this and the installation and the downloading will basically start.
Once the downloading is started just double click this do next next next and all the installation will
be done.
Okay.
Now how to start a VS code after the installation is done okay.
So right now I have the exe file.
I have already done the installation.
I will go to my folder.
Let's say that I want to start my Python programming language from this particular folder.
So I've created a Data Analyst Boot Camp folder.
Inside that I've created a Python folder.
Okay.
So from this particular folder what I will do I will go ahead and write my command prompt okay.
So I will open my command prompt inside this command prompt.
And remember you have to start this process after you install this.
But still this is getting downloaded.
Once it gets downloaded, just double click this.
Click on next, next next and on the installation will basically happen.
Okay, now I will go ahead and open my command prompt.
I will go to this specific folder location.
Right.
So I will say CD e this particular drive right.
So what did I do over here?
I wrote CD and this path that I have actually taken, I have just pasted it over here.
Okay.
Like this I'm pasting it over here.
So here it is.
And I will go to my e drive.
So here you can see once I go to my E drive automatically I'm going in that specific path.
Not only this, if you want to go ahead and start from here also you can go ahead and do it, you know.
So here if I do right click here.
You can see I'm getting open with code right.
If you are installing it for the first time, probably you may not get it right.
So here you can see my VS code is basically exe file is installed.
So if I double click this here you can see setup has detected that Visual Studio code is currently running.
Please close all the instances then click okay to continue.
So already my installation is done.
So I'm not going to do that.
But for you it will just keep on coming next next next.
And you can start now.
Once I go to my command prompt in this particular folder location.
Okay I will just go ahead and write code dot.
Once I write code dot, please make sure that you note this particular command.
Once I write code dot automatically my VS code will get opened in that specific folder location.
So here you can probably see Python right?
So once you have this particular Python you can go ahead and start your coding.
Right.
You can probably create a file let's say test dot ipynb file.
And you can start your coding.
Okay.
But this is more about coding.
We will see in the next video.
But I hope I've shown you how you can open the VS code, how you can do the installation of the VS code.
And all right, so two things I've actually focused on this particular video.
One was downloading your anaconda.
One was setting up your path environment.
Make sure to do that check box okay.
And the second thing that you really need to download is your VS code.
That is Visual Studio Code.
Double click it, install it.
Then in any folder location, let's say in this Python folder location, what I've done through my command
prompt, I've gone to this particular location and I've just written code space dot.
Once I write code space dot, my VS code will get opened.
So I hope you are able to understand this particular video in this entire course.
I'm going to use VS code as my ID, but if you still face any problem because of some or the other thing,
you can even start with Google Colab, right?
If you still face any kind of issues, please make sure that you write down in the discussion forum.
Right?
So yes, this was it from my side.
I will see you in the next video.
Thank you.